<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>linux on Daniel&#39;s programming rants</title>
    <link>https://gerlacdt.github.io/tags/linux/</link>
    <description>Recent content in linux on Daniel&#39;s programming rants</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Jan 2023 11:00:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://gerlacdt.github.io/tags/linux/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Effective CLI (more productive than an IDE!)</title>
      <link>https://gerlacdt.github.io/posts/effective-cli/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jan 2023 11:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gerlacdt.github.io/posts/effective-cli/</guid>
      <description>TL;DR  Modern Terminal with nice (Nerd) Fonts ZSH oh-my-zsh Modern Prompt with starship Modern CLI tools (fzf, ripgrep, bat, tmux, jq) Fast editor (Emacs, Neovim, Helix) Organize your dotfiles with GNU Stow  The Unix shell/Command-Line Interface (CLI) is an ancient tool. Despite being around forever, the shell is highly customizable and with a good configuration, it is on par with modern graphical IDEs. Because it is configurable, you can make it truly your own, thereby surpassing out-of-the-box experience of IDEs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Install Postgres on Ubuntu</title>
      <link>https://gerlacdt.github.io/posts/postgres-ubuntu/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jul 2019 10:15:34 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gerlacdt.github.io/posts/postgres-ubuntu/</guid>
      <description>Recently i decided to switch from MacOS to Linux. I was already an Ubuntu user from 2006 till 2015. So i am used to Linux. Nevertheless i struggled a little bit with the installation of PostgreSQL. For MacOS there is a nice all-in-one package which i recommend: Postgres.app. Everything works out-of-the-box there. In Ubuntu, on the other hand, we need to adjust the default installation a little bit in order to start application development.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Find and Replace in multiple files</title>
      <link>https://gerlacdt.github.io/posts/find-and-replace/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Apr 2019 10:13:14 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gerlacdt.github.io/posts/find-and-replace/</guid>
      <description>As a software programmer you often have to search and replace a specific string in multiple files because of a refactoring or just improving a variable or function name.
Normally you can use your IDE or your editor for this. But in bigger codebases with thousand or million lines of code it can be very slow. Neither do IDEs work with remote SSH-sessions. In such situations the command-line is pretty handy.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ag the_silver_searcher, a grep replacement</title>
      <link>https://gerlacdt.github.io/posts/ag-silver-searcher/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Apr 2019 10:04:01 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gerlacdt.github.io/posts/ag-silver-searcher/</guid>
      <description>As a programmer you often search for a specific strings or regexps in multiple files. Previously i used to do this with the well-known GNU-tools find and grep.
The following command searches for main in all *.go files in the current directory and:
1 2  find . -iname &amp;#39;*.go&amp;#39; | xargs grep -inH &amp;#34;main&amp;#34; # -i ignore case, -n print line number, -H print filename   Recently i discovered ag the silver searcher.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
