<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>softwareengineering on Daniel&#39;s programming rants</title>
    <link>https://gerlacdt.github.io/tags/softwareengineering/</link>
    <description>Recent content in softwareengineering on Daniel&#39;s programming rants</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 04 Nov 2022 10:00:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://gerlacdt.github.io/tags/softwareengineering/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Reading List Programming Books</title>
      <link>https://gerlacdt.github.io/posts/programming-books/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Nov 2022 10:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gerlacdt.github.io/posts/programming-books/</guid>
      <description>This article contains a list of my favorite books with a major impact on my Software Engineering career. The books are categorized in:
 Software Engineering Programming Brian Kernighan’s Books Modern Classics Learning Management and Leadership Unix Books From Stevens  Software Engineering A Philosophy of Software Design by John Ousterhout
Link to book
A fabulous book to level up your software design skills as an experienced engineer. The book is full of great advice.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Software Engineering and Feedback Loops</title>
      <link>https://gerlacdt.github.io/posts/software-engineering-feedback-loops/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2022 10:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gerlacdt.github.io/posts/software-engineering-feedback-loops/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Most of the breakthrough inventions in historic and modern Software Engineering are related to feedback loops. They are essential for productive software development, Developer Effectiveness and Developer Happiness. Remember the dawn of computing when computers were programmed with punch cards, programmers had to turn in their cards over night and the next day they got the result &amp;ndash; often with a compile error 😞. Unlike back then, today&amp;rsquo;s computers compile whole codebases in seconds.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing better Code</title>
      <link>https://gerlacdt.github.io/posts/writing-better-software/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Aug 2020 18:38:45 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gerlacdt.github.io/posts/writing-better-software/</guid>
      <description>In Joel Spolsky&amp;rsquo;s blog post &amp;ldquo;The Joel Test: 12 Steps to better Code&amp;rdquo;, he describes a test composed of twelve simple yes-no questions. For a yes you get one point. 10 points are acceptable and 12 are perfect. If you have less than 10 points, you will get in trouble with your software &amp;ndash; sooner or later.
For a quick self-check, these are the original questions:
 Do you use source control?</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
